The final is tonight.
We have 18 divers and 12 of them will make it through to tonight's showpiece final Well, it only seems like yesterday we were here.
In fact, it was it was last night Qualification finished well after 10 o'clock UK time now It's just before 10 a.m. And 18 of last night's 32 divers are back here and ready to compete again
taking the travelling time to and from the Athletes' Village and these divers like Tom Daley here will be lucky to have got six or seven hours sleep.
The British diver getting a massive round of applause from another impressive crowd here.
Tom Daley was one of the divers who had an inconsistent evening in qualification.
Steve Rebellion is alongside me yet again once the cheering for the local hero dies down and Steve how surprised are you at this schedule?
They're back here so quickly aren't they?
They are and I just worry that it doesn't allow the athletes to give of their best because as you point out we finished here about 10.20, 10.15 last night they may have got back to the village by 11
They may have needed a massage, something to eat.
If they got to sleep by midnight, I'd be very surprised.
And then they're going to be up by 6.30.
And operating on six hours sleep is just not ideal.
So the scheduling is curious at best.
And it was a very long session last night that they had.
And in fact they're in that there would have been maybe a couple of these guys required to do a drug test, which would have held them back even further.
So the scheduling has raised a few eyebrows, but I think that said, we're in for a great competition if last night's is anything to go by.
And the two Chinese boys are going to be very difficult to remove from top spot.
Lin Ye and Xu Bo were absolutely outstanding with their skill level and their consistency across the six dives.
Yes, the dive order today is seeded from yesterday's qualification process.
I still get the feeling it doesn't really reflect the true talent that's out there in the diving pool.
The Mexicans and the Germans had excellent evenings like Martin Wolfram who've got themselves in good positions and can watch the dives unfold.
Last night's competition with 32 divers took
more than three hours to compete so there was half an hour wait between each dive for each diver and interesting to read some of the overnight quotes from the divers saying how difficult they found it and didn't know quite how to handle it Matthew Mitchum said a really experienced diver like like himself Tom Daly who was very inconsistent said that his legs felt tired at the end and I've got a feeling we really haven't seen the real competition emerge
apart from as you said those two Chinese superstars at the top of the order.
Another indication that for some at least it was a long night three of the top six divers their last dive was their worst and then look at someone like Gleb Galperin who
just staggered across the line in the end, but his ranking across the night, he started second, then second after the second dive, then fifth, fifth, fifteenth and sixteenth, and he only just made it.
So there you see Gleb Galper and the Russian going off third, which means he was third last to qualify, and his was a surprising performance, but indicative of the inconsistency we saw.
Well, last night, many of these top divers who can pull out a top-scoring performance with one single effort had a little bit of slack in their program.
They could afford maybe to dip their standards a little bit.
But now we're getting to this semifinal stage, and even more so tonight.
A mistake, a poor dive, will be really costly.
I really think we're going to see the whole level crank up here this morning and certainly the pressure will increase.
Those lapses are not going to be allowed.
It was a long night for the judges too who have to assess these dives.
They have one look at it, they don't get the advantage of the excellent TV replays which we can all enjoy.
Seven judges, the top two and the bottom two marks are discounted.
It's very clear when you see the score captions come up at the end of each dive.
And the only ones who really managed that terrific consistency were Lin Yue here and Chu Bo, his Chinese compatriot.
They were incredible.
The big feature of these Chinese divers is that they never seem to let their standard drop.
Excellent is like their bottom line.
David Badiat, silver medalist at the World Championships last year, again someone who had an inconsistent night, he's come in in the last place and so will go off first and all the divers that have made the semi-final are doing the same six dives as they did in the qualifying, the preliminary.
We're getting a look at Tom Daly there.
He is the Great Britain poster boy, one of the faces of the build-up to these London 2012 Olympic Games.
Been under tremendous pressure of expectation and this crowd, so many of them who will probably be new to this sport but they know it's spectacular and they will be willing daily along after a difficult evening for him but
He is by no means the only star of the show for you to enjoy.
Not far from a start then.
David Badiah will lead us off with an arm stand back double somersault two and a half twists and the different strategies about where you put your high tariff dives start off with one which is going to be the case for David.
Just a reminder, every dive has a degree of difficulty or a tariff, it's 3.6 this, and that figure is multiplied by the sum of the three middle scores they get.
And now the diving pool can settle down and await the start of competition with David Budaya from the United States, 23-year-old from Abilene in Texas, getting us underway with an arm stand back double somersault, two and a half twist, which is a strong opening dive.
Solid start from him and this was one of his better dives last night.
It hauled in 81 points and with the higher tariff dives, decent execution is going to get you a healthy score and start as you intend to finish.
Well, this is very promising for David.
Minimal splash.
Good angle of entry.
And an 88.2.
So straight off, he's improved on his beginning from last night.
Next up is Jose Guerra of Cuba.
forward three and a half somersault piked for Grela who like quite a few of these divers also competed in the 10 meter synchro event where he finished in fifth position.
Much lower tariff on this dive which he's executed well he's going to get eights and eight and a halfs but he won't score as highly as David Baddaya.
somewhat mucked up his first dive last night it was this one he only had 58.5 so 76.5 well there's an improvement as well and a significant one by some 18 points that's huge so he's on his way momentum and confidence so important to these divers through the competition now this is gleb galperin who had a storming start he's 27 years of age very experienced but had a horrendous amount of injury
And again, he started well.
He's controlled that entry beautifully and just flattened the water, pulled the air down with him.
And he opened with an 88 yesterday.
And he's the one who's going to have to deal with the upcoming applause and performance of Tom Daly.
But.
Eight and a half across the board, pretty much from the judges and an 81.6.
Right from the moment the crowd realised that next up is Tom Daley.
A controlled degree of bedlam breaks out.
I think that reflects the anxiety everybody feels for this young, teenage superstar.
Second Olympics, competing when he was just 14 in Beijing.
What a camera angle that is, Tom Daley.
Back, two and a half somersault, two and a half twist.
Well it was a good entry but if on our angle we could see that he wasn't quite square to the side of the pool and that leg angle may well have been caught by the judges.
Very difficult with this amount of twisting to line yourself up properly and he has been marked down a little for that.
He opened with a 73.8 yesterday.
So it's just slightly twisted to the angle he desired.
And an 81 though, so he too has found some improvement when it matters.
PA announcer asking the very enthusiastic crowd here to refrain from taking flash photographs, not wanting to distract the divers at all.
Victor from Russia.
Opening dives and in with three and a half somersault tucked.
Just 3.2 the tariff here.
Long hold at the top here.
Well, he does a good job in the end.
We always get a little concerned when they spend that much time at the top.
As we discussed, it's like not being able to put the putter on the ball in golf.
It's almost the yips, but it's a slightly dangerous dive as they come in close with their head, as you can see, but he had more margin for error than perhaps that camera angle suggested.
Only sevens yesterday for that dive, so he too.
This is a great start to the competition, Roger.
They're all lifting their performance.
It's Victor's first Olympic Games.
He's a European silver medalist on the platform.
Moving on now to Victor Ortega with a back two and a half somersault, one and a half twists.
24 year old from Columbia.
And then there is the first sort of significant error on entry coming from Victor Ortega.
75.2 for this opening dive yesterday.
But it'll be a lower return today.
Slightly messy entry.
All good to this point and then just missed times the kick out and the feet were slightly apart.
Side on the judges aren't going to see that so much.
About 68.8.
So he's given up about seven marks on that opening dive from yesterday.
Ukraine's Anton Zakharov, 26 years of age, has been competing at the highest level for more than a decade.
First World Championships were back in 2001, in with three and a half somersault tucked.
That was beautifully done.
And you just caught a hint of that gas where the crowd doesn't like to see their head and body go that close to the end of the platform.
But Anton knew what he was doing.
Oh, that is close.
This is going to be higher than yesterday and to seventy two for his first dive.
How close?
That close.
I don't know.
Twenty centimeters.
A lot of good height up off that platform to give himself the room and time to get through the somersaults before he can straighten out to make the perfect entry or as near perfect as he can make it.
76.8, healthy start as we move on to Riley McCormick.
The Canadian who's 21 later this month.
Forward three and a half somersault pint to get off an under way.
Well, it was alright.
He had a little bit too much forward momentum out into the pool to create the vertical entry.
But there's a lot of somersaults to get through here.
Took it very close to the platform before throwing himself out into the into the ether there.
72 to see him get more than that.
A number of these competitors who have made the last 18 did not start well.
McCormick was one and Aguirre was another.
Aguirre from Cuba forward three and a half somersault to open.
He got to the semifinal in Beijing four years ago.
So his ambition at least will be to go one step further and make the top 12 after this morning's competition.
Better first dive.
It's only got a low tariff of three.
Yesterday only sixty one and a half.
Created an interesting angle for himself there coming from that side of the platform.
Seventy two.
Big cheer goes up for the defending Olympic champion who had a patchy night.
Matthew Mitchum from Australia, one of the big names of the platform.
He never knew quite what to expect from Mr Mitchum Eminem last night.
But he's got the big one in his locker, always capable of pulling out something spectacular.
If his somewhat injured body allows it, he admits that he can't put in as much difficulty as he would like because he's got some limitations now.
This dive itself just a tariff of three and he's pulled good scores for it and opening 75 just under what he did last night.
Just an update there on the standings to date but it's a little bit misleading because the top guys are still to go towards the end of the round.
Nick McCrory from the United States, 21 year old, already got a bronze in the synchro.
In with three and a half somersault.
Nicely finished.
Well through in somersaults to spot the water, get the entry just right.
into a tight tuck, knees up to the shoulders and control the entry pretty well.
See better ripped entries than this.
Straight eights to count there.
Seventy-six point eight zero.
Alexander Bondar now from Ukraine.
Another one of the impressive number of teenagers in this competition.
Just eighteen
Oh, excellent start.
He had five very good dives last night and one terrible one, his third.
We'll keep an eye on that one.
He scored under 60, but he's commenced well again here.
All the power going through the toes on the end of the platform.
And quickly through the somersaults to give him plenty of time to find a good entry.
didn't have a great synchro competition, finished eighth with Oleksandr Kovarsov after finishing third in the ten meter synchro in last year's world championship.
So, he's got a little bit more to come out still.
Now, the Mexican divers are having a a good games and a good competition at ten meters as well.
This is Ivan Garcia.
Forward four and a half somersault with a
Well, he's done a nice job of it.
We're into the top six now, and we've got two competitors from three nations, Mexico, Mexico, then Germany, Germany, and then the top seeded two Chinese.
A lot to get through here.
And that's a great position he finds as he enters and keeps the splash to a minimum.
So he's drawn very respectable scores there and an 88.8 to open with.
Garcia has a silver medal from the 10 metre synchro with his
countryman German Sanchez, who's now on the board for a back three and a half somersault.
So these two divers have already performed impressively and are still going strong.
This was the top scoring dive in the first round last night.
Oh, and it might well be again.
An 89.1 last night for German Sanchez with nines across the board.
He has absolutely controlled this.
He's in the flyweight division, seven stone six pounds, that's 47 kilos his body weight, which is extremely light.
Judge is not feeling quite as generous as in the prelims and an 85.8 as opposed to his 89 from last night, but pretty close.
as the standard rises in this competition inevitably the judges will be a little bit more pushed to be a little bit more stingy with their marking like that they're really gonna have to work for it but we've not been dazzled by tens i'm sure that's still to come possibly tonight when the competition really hots up martin wolfram now who's had a very good competition to date arm stand back double somersault two and a half twist
Well, pretty good effort.
He's the 12th ranked dive in the first round last night, 77.4.
But you'll have observed, as we did, that the splash was a bit more than he would have liked.
Maybe just a little bit short of vertical on entry.
And a 91.8, though.
Well, the judges did like it.
Lifts him to top spot for the moment.
Very early days.
His countryman Sacha Klein dives next.
26 year old.
In with three and a half somersault tucked.
3.2 the tariff.
Silver medalist in Beijing in the 10 metre synchro.
Again nice and tight into the end of the platform.
He's got plenty of experience I think compared to his countryman Wolfram who's only 20 and experience is going to count increasingly as they go through these rounds trying to keep that consistency.
76.8.
He's dropped about five marks on his opening dive from the prelims and now our top two men class apart really
Lin Yue, 21-year-old from Guangdong, in with three and a half somersault.
Well, solid.
He'll improve.
It was his second dive that brought him undone last night.
Well, he's undone, he finished second, but he ended up with a 17th ranked dive in the second series.
He had several nines with his opening dive yesterday but not quite so high here and an eighty-one six.
Now, the man who's been setting the standards, Chubo, 19 years of age, the favorite for the gold
Well he was there so early he gets through the somersaults in the blink of an eye and he seems to have so much time to get the entry right which of course he's done this is his lowest tariff dive and it was his lowest scoring dive last night he just says he doesn't even particularly like this dive but he's getting nine so nine and a half
He must be the only person in the pool that doesn't like it.
Everybody else can only admire it.
Absolutely impassive through competition, isn't he?
89.6.
He's found an extra three marks there.
And that completes the first series.
12, a cut-off point, remember?
Martin Wolfram.
It's his first Olympic Games.
He's really untested at this level and he's performing superbly.
Chubo, Ivan, Garcia.
The Mexican boy is well placed here, third and fifth.
Sasha Klein, more to come from him and three divers there linked on 11th.
If they were level on points at the end of six dives, then they would all go through.
There's no count back or anything like that in diving that they would share qualification and if it comes to tonight, they'd share a medal as well.
Just a little surprising to see Sasha Klein down the list there.
He was never out of the top five in the prelim.
David Budaya from studying communications at Purdue University West Lafayette in Indiana.
Second dive in with three and a half somersault.
Nicely handled again from David.
This wasn't one of his better dives last night.
Well, but the judges like what they've seen here, the very impressive entry and very quickly through his somersaults, nice leg form and an 86.4.
He's come to compete now.
He was a bit rusty last night.
we knew that 18th was no reflection of David's potential.
Jose from Cuba now back three and a half somersault and again massively improved on last night.
Well, that dive for him last night was nothing short of a disaster.
He got 21.6.
It was barely a dive at all.
He's crashed into the water well short and he'll be relieved to have got it out of the way.
And with the eights being announced.
He's the senior pro on duty today.
He's 33 years of age, the oldest competitor in the pool today.
So 88.2 compared to 21.6 and that is a massive improvement and maybe he is heading for the final.
That will be Gleb Galparin's aim.
Had eight operations on back and knee problems and missed a couple of years through injury.
This is an arm stand reverse triple somersault.
Oh dear.
Well short.
And that was a dive that got him 91.8 in the prelims.
Never looked in control really of the armstand.
And the legs far from vertical.
So that's potentially eliminating him.
37.4.
Depends what the others do and if he can nail a few big dives.
But now, Tom Daley.
He was Britain's youngest team member at just 14 years of age four years ago in Beijing.
He's had some four years to contend with since.
In with three and a half somersault tucked for the 18 year old.
That's a super entry and the crowd recognises that and they're going to work on the judges now to get their man a big score.
Fantastic reception.
Every mum in that crowd wishes their daughter would bring Tom home for tea.
He's just got that sort of look.
He does, and he's absolutely mastered this dive, keeping it in tight to the end of the platform.
He was operating on minimal sleep.
He wanted to be here early, getting lots of practice before this session.
He was quite disappointed in himself.
And at 86.4, he's found another eight marks on that dive alone.
Victor Minibaev from Russia.
forward four and a half somersault three point seven the tariff here and you can expect victor to attack this dive all the way one of the quite physical eastern european more powerful looking divers good job it was his top scoring dive last night he wants it in the 80s again 86.95
That's what it brought him at the first attempt.
Just slightly past the vertical.
A couple of eights and seven and a halfs in there.
86.95.
That's exactly what he had last night, there you go.
We talk about consistency.
Victor Ortega from Colombia now, straight into his forward three and a half somersault.
Some of them really, as soon as they get the call, they want to go, don't they?
This is a bit disappointing for a taker.
It's a low tariff dive.
His lowest, in fact, 3.0.
And he's not done such a great job in a lovely pike position.
Just rolled the feet over and created a big splash.
But nose to knees, very flexible, beautiful position through the air.
Just didn't quite finish it off.
And a sixty-three only.
Well, the low tariff hurts that dive.
Anton Zakharov from Ukraine.
World Championship silver and bronze in the past at the synchro events.
Back three and a half somersault now.
Very good.
Look, he wasn't quite vertical but somehow he controlled
the entry and the better divers can do this you think they're in trouble when they hit the water but they pull the air down with them and it minimizes the splash his angle was slightly off too but only catch that on the second look Roger this is the judges just don't see everything it's too quick and he's got an eighty six point four nearly as good as last night's eighty eight two
When the hands come together as they prepare for entry into the water, they're not just punching a hole through the water, they're punching a hole through the air as well.
They're traveling at such speed.
Riley McCormick now from Canada, back two and a half somersault, two and a half twist, three point six, the degree of difficulty here.
Sitting eleventh.
Done a nice job there.
He looked a little twitchy on the platform.
I wondered how many little flexes of the ankles there were going to be until he went.
They've got good power off the platform.
His feet a little loose.
Reasonable entry and he should get a reasonable score.
But you see the ankles drifting apart there.
The judges don't want to see that.
And you don't want them to see it if you're the diver.
But an eighty-six four, I don't think they saw much of it.
There were a couple of form problems there, but we can just stress again that the judges just don't catch what we can see on the slow motion.
They get one look.
Aguila from Cuba.
Down in 16th now has an inward three and a half somersault tucked to try to improve that.
Oh my goodness, he was tight to the end of the platform.
That gasp from the crowd as they worry about contact.
This was his top scoring dive last night.
He got nines, a couple of nine and a halfs in fact.
Oh, that's too close for me.
That is solid concrete up there.
Not a bad idea to have that towel there.
That would at least help if there was any contact.
But there's a disturbing range here.
I don't like seeing six up to eight.
That's great despair.
That just tells you that one judge saw something that others didn't or thought they did.
Matthew Mitchum now.
Brisbane Bourne lives in Sydney studying language and science at Sydney University.
Back three and a half somersault for one of the big names in diving.
Oh, that's an entry.
He looks in a little better form.
He doesn't look like a gold medallist, but he's got something going better than last night.
Well, he's done again a good job with an entry that wasn't vertical.
And an eighty-five point eight for Matthew.
Trying to become only the fifth man to retain ten metre Olympic title.
That'll be a quiz question on the other four as the competition unfolds.
I've got a piece of
We can both look clever.
That's right.
Nick McCrory now from the United States.
Arm stand back, double somersault, one and a half twist.
He's also linked there in 11th place.
Long hold again.
He managed that alright.
There wasn't a lot of power off the platform from the arm stand.
It was more out into the pool and up.
But that was how he executed the dive last night.
When he left the platform, the arms were pretty straight.
Not a lot of power coming here at this moment.
Some of it's generated by the legs, of course, as they flick out.
Good position on entry.
Coach looks satisfied, if not thrilled.
An 83.2.
Fractionally better than his first attempt last night.
Alexander Bondar from the Ukraine.
18 years of age.
Forward four and a half somersault.
3.7.
A little messy at the finish.
Four and a half somersaults.
Good tariff offered here.
Three point seven.
But getting it just right is what the divers have found difficult with this one.
He was competing at European Junior Championship level just last year.
So it is a massive step up for an 18 year old to suddenly find himself diving against the absolute cream.
Seventy seven seven.
He's given up about six points on the same dive last night.
First of the two Mexican divers, Ivan Garcia.
He's 18 years of age, the younger of the two.
Back three and a half somersault.
This was his best dive last night.
Tucked position.
Oh, that's great.
You know, the analogy with the gymnastics for that kind of dive is it's like a blind landing as you're just reaching back, searching for the water.
They spot the ceiling a couple of times, three times, kick out, get themselves vertical.
That's what the training's all about, being able to do that.
With these back somersaults.
Now he kicks out.
Now he finds the vertical.
That's really well done.
And an 87-4-5.
Well done.
Judges really like that.
Now it's his synchro silver medal teammate, German Sanchez.
His forward two and a half somersault three twists in the piked position.
Piked, the legs are out straight and they're clutching around the back of the knees, the tucked when they're curled up into a little ball.
A lot to get through there wasn't it?
There was and he got through it all but compromising the entry I think.
See how vertical he gets here and just flipped the, he was a little bent at the hips in the end.
Barely timing that for the public position to actually get into it, he's almost out of it as soon as he's into it.
91.2 though with that decent tariff of 3.8.
Martin Wolfram competing at the highest level of his short career and responding to the challenge leading after the first round in with three and a half somersaults
Well, he didn't really get on top of this dive last night.
He's got a 72 for it.
It's his lowest tariff, 3.2.
So if he can get more than 72, oh, he's going to.
The judges love this one.
Well, his entry is near perfect.
a more straightforward dive.
You really do want to be making the most of the entry and Martin's done that with an eighty-six point four and a low tariff dive.
That's an excellent return.
Very impressive Olympic debut.
Sasha Klein, his older, more experienced countrymen.
Eight gold and two silver at
He's got some support here, though they both have, Sacha Klein and Martin Wolfram.
And why not?
This one earned him 88.8 last night.
Might be a very similar score, high 80s perhaps for Sacha.
Well, 90.65, even better.
It's just so impressed Roger to see so many divers just finding another three, five, ten points.
Lin Yue needs to do that as well.
He was sixth after the first dive.
Reverse three and a half somersault there.
He's a man with high expectations.
This is his first time he's competed at the very highest level in an individual event.
Normally it's been synchro success.
This was the dive that troubled him last night.
74.25 last night with seven and a halfs but much better effort here.
Totally in control from the moment he left the platform.
And that is a very small splash from 10 metres.
And a 94.05.
Three nine and a halfs count.
Only one nine.
I don't think we've seen so many nine and a halves in a set of figures so far.
Chou Bo, the world champion, number one favorite for this, the 19 year old from Sichuan with a arm stand back triple somersault worth 3.5.
Oh well there is a rare identifiable mistake from Choubo.
This was a dive got him 99.75 last night but he's a little bent initially in the pike and short on entry.
So he is human.
Yes.
course in Rome in 2009 in the World Championships it came down to the last three dives with himself and Matthew Mitchum and Tom Daley and Chubo didn't produce the dive on the day and nor did Matthew Mitchum and that was when Tom Daley stole the title so
Maybe just that little seed of doubt knows that he's very aware that things can go wrong.
But Martin Wolfram is really storming in this semi-final.
It is just a semi-final.
The Mexicans again, and those two Chinese divers in fourth and fifth, that's not their sort of natural diving habitat.
and it's on daily ninth there.
Sasha Klein has dropped a little bit.
David Budaya now starting to emerge in twelfth.
Matthew Mitcham is where the cutoff is but he's only point eight ahead of Nick McCrory, Riley McCormick.
So, there's plenty more that can happen and Gleb Galper in down at the bottom there holding up the rest at the moment but the two Chinese divers just being given something to think about.
that satisfy themselves in the knowledge that the scores don't carry forward to the final, just have to make the 12 and then start again, start afresh.
If there were one or two dives that didn't please you, you don't have to worry about them.
There is that advantage, perhaps, if you do dive last.
You do know at least what you've got to do.
You also know, of course, that there's nobody else who can make a mistake.
So it is all down to you.
David Budaya kicks us off having a much, much better series of dives so far.
This forward four and a half somersault tucked is worth 3.7.
Very tidy as his top scoring dive in the prelims with an 88.8.
It's a bit of a rush to reach the vertical with this dive because there's so many somersaults to get through.
Just powers off the end of the platform.
In fact, he almost over rotated it, didn't he?
But to control the entry once more, he's having a much better session here second time around.
Remember, this is the guy who does confess that he has a bit of a fear of heights, which is a strange complaint when you want to be a 10-meter platform diver.
That's a new high mark for him into the 90s.
He didn't manage that last night.
So he's come to compete.
Jose Guerra from Cuba.
Down in tenth position, in with three and a half somersault, three point two.
So he can't afford to get too much wrong here.
We got it all right.
And again, that's close, isn't it?
You take out his disastrous second dive in the prelims with a 21.6 that we've referred to a couple of times.
How much further up the rankings would he have been?
Give him another 50 points.
He's got the good dives coming.
Gleb Gauperin, the 27-year-old from Moscow.
Double world champion, double Olympic bronze.
He's the man, remember, who's had all the injury worries.
Forward three and a half, somersault there.
Just a 3.0 degree of difficulty.
So Galperin had some problems with his second dive.
Low tariff here.
He's going to have to fight back with his last three.
Good scores, but only a three tariff.
So 72.
You'll know what's coming next with Peter Waterfield having a really disappointing evening last night.
Tom Daley is carrying British hopes entirely on his young shoulders.
Arm stand back, triple somersault, 3.5.
No towel for extra grip for Tom.
See how long he holds the dive right at the top.
This was Tom's top scoring dive in prelims with an 89.
Very impressive on the platform.
Looks so in control.
Good push.
Just not quite 100% vertical with the entry.
But the judges are going to like most of this.
crowd trying to put a little bit of pressure on the judges to maybe convince them that it was slightly better than it was.
So he's not 100% vertical and he's not 100% square either, but it's a very good dive in every other aspect.
Great line, toes pointed from fingers to toes.
And an 84 there, just five points short of last night's effort.
Victor from Russia.
Reverse three and a half somersault tucked.
Experiencing in a big games for the first time.
Very composed and waiting.
He's got his mind completely right and clear.
jumped well away from the platform, but that didn't compromise the somersaults or his entry position.
This dive too, from that standing position close to the platform, you can have a worry, but he took that out of the equation in a bar by taking himself well away.
Lots of clearance room there.
to compromise those if you jump out rather than up.
You can find yourself short of time but not that.
Seventy-nine point two is very solid.
Columbia's Victor Ortega who was taken diving when he was just three years of age.
He's back in seventeenth position.
So, this arm stand back triple somersault
Oh well it didn't really.
Larger splash, didn't control the entry.
So just modest scores coming in in the sevens.
3.3 the difficulty.
We discussed that tattoo.
It's about his love of life.
Life in Spanish is a Vita.
But it's life.
69-3, that's life.
Don't always get the scores you want.
Whoever said life is supposed to be fair.
Anton Sakharov next.
He's just above the cut at 11th, this forward four and a half somersault.
Oh, nice.
Very good.
Of this four and a half somersault.
The divers have attempted it.
This is one of the better efforts.
Very tight tuck position.
And eights across the board for Zakharov.
Not much to complain about there.
Not much to deduct.
So they don't.
Eighty eight point eight.
The Chinese would think that was a lucky dive with all those eights.
That's the lucky number.
I think they prefer a hundred and eight.
Don't rule it out.
Riley McCormick from Canada.
Trains and studies at Arizona State University in the States.
This is an inward three and a half somersault and he's just out of the picture in 14th at the moment.
Eric Sane went out to the competition last night.
Canada would be disappointed if they didn't have a finalist in this 10 metre competition.
McCoury's going to have to find something in the second half of this semi-final.
That was close to just the feet rolled over a little.
just to leave less than the 100% impression for the judges.
Eighty-one six.
Going to be tight around that cutoff point.
from Cuba.
Back three and a half somersault.
a couple of Olympic Games, two World Championships.
He would regard a final position as reward for the training and the dedication.
Oh dear.
Well, he had trouble with his dive last night.
Sixty-four point eight only and the judges aren't going to be too
His issues with the entry.
He was well short.
Almost disastrously so in terms of the scores.
Fives and a five and a half for fifty five point eight and that will be tough to recover from.
The defending champion, Matthew Mitcham.
Only non-Chinese diver to winner medal in Beijing.
Ruined for clean sweep.
In with three and a half somersault now.
Oh, beautiful.
He's back to near his best.
3.2 yes he does like it he loves a smile for the camera doesn't he he loves this stage well he is a showman and to be fair even during the difficulties last night he came up smiling and waving at the camera
I think he's one of those athletes, Roger, who just finds it a joy to be here.
Wow, I'm at the Olympics.
He's done it all before, but he just thrives on it.
And an 86.4 for Matthew.
So he's picked up another five points on his prelim effort for the same dive.
If he's feeling enjoyment and no pressure, that makes him even more dangerous if he can relax into his diving.
Nick McCrory now from the United States, 13th.
That was a forward four and a half somersault with a three point seven tariff, which he will have been looking to cash in on.
He just sounded a little heavy footed on the platform and I'm not quite sure he really had a vertical body on the entry here.
The replay will show us not that the judges see this, but he was just still working his way out.
of the somersaults as he entered the water and so still bent at the hips.
So just held him back a little on his marks because of that.
83.25.
High tariff.
So that helps.
Alexander Bondar from Ukraine.
Fifteenth arm stand back, double somersault, two and a half twist.
This was his problem last night, 57.6 for this dive.
So keep your fingers crossed for him.
Long hold.
Well, it's better than last night, but there's still room there.
It's a real worry when they stay up there that long.
The ankles were never together until entry, really, and it wasn't quite vertical, but he's got away with one in terms of improvement from last night.
Leg form was pretty ropey.
One of the great things about the Games is how you sense that the crowd are supporting every competitor.
Obviously the Brits are getting a massive support, but you do feel in those long pauses the crowd are willing them to do it well.
He's picked up 25 points there, Bondoy.
High tariff on that dive, even though there were a couple of faults.
Ivan Garcia is carrying on from where he left off last night.
At least inward four and a half somersault four point one.
This is a big dive and he's in third place after his opening two dives.
Four and a half somersaults from a standing start.
You've got to be quick.
He was pretty quick.
I was just looking to see how much knee bend there was going to be as he launched off the platform.
Not a great deal really.
He still generated good power.
And the feet just came apart for that finish.
That's such a shame to get from the split tuck to get the ankles together.
Timing.
Not easy.
And an 86.1.
Long hold at the top.
You can feel the 15,000 odd people just all holding their breath, wondering when he's going to make that decision to launch.
We were a little bit critical of that dive, but he still picked up nine points on the same one from last night.
When I say we, it was me, wasn't it?
Thank you.
German Sanchez from Mexico.
Second after the opening couple of dives.
Arm stand back, triple somersault, and again the pool hushed.
Oh dear.
Entry-wise, that's a disaster at this level, and he will be punished.
The judges do not like to see that, even if you do a lot right before then, which he seemed to do, but the timing was wrong.
Came out too early, over-rotated, massive splash, and he's under five right across.
Three and a half, four,
Well, he'll get away with that in the semifinal stage, having had such an impressive start, but that's got to go if he's there tonight.
Martin Wolfram has been outstanding.
Reverse three and a half somersault.
Top of the pile at the moment.
He may stay there.
That was a good effort.
The degree of difficulty will just hold him back a little, a 3.3.
He competed here in February, that World Cup event, which gave many of the divers a chance to sample the atmosphere and the water.
He was ninth in the 10-meter platform then, but he is a bit of an unknown quantity and maybe one or two of the others will be wondering just how much this guy's got in his locker.
79.2 for Martin.
His lowest dive so far.
Sasha Klein up next who slipped back a bit after good work last night and the start of today.
Now he's got an arm stand back, triple somersault with 3.5 the tariff.
He's in eighth place.
Well this was his top dive in the prelims and maybe it will be again.
92.75 last night for Sasha.
Takes a lovely pike position.
He did get a couple of nines for it last night.
Eight and a halfs and eights.
So not quite as good.
Delightful to watch.
Well executed.
And an 89 to 5.
Seems fairly happy with the way the competition is going.
I wonder if the same can be said for Lin Yue, who will have only the very highest level of expectations.
He's fourth after two rounds, back three and a half somersault.
Oh, he's nailed it again.
That was the only 100 point dive last night.
Even Chou Bow couldn't eclipse this one.
Oh, he's just perfect through the air.
Unbelievable, the nine and a half's come in.
And we're heading for three digits here.
He got a ten there that's going to be taken out.
But three nine and a halfs and a one hundred and two point six.
There it is.
Our first hundred point dive in the semi.
There may well be a competition within the competition between these two Chinese teammates and rivals, of course, Chubo now reverse three and a half somersault and a disappointing second dive, which is really quite out of character.
He's back.
That's not a 100-point dive because he doesn't have the tariff, but the form is there.
See how much deeper into a squat he gets to drive up off the platform.
He has got a history of landing plenty of 10s.
25 perfect tens in a series back in 2011, a FINA Diving World Series event in Beijing.
94.05, exactly the same mark as that dive yielded last night.
Now, this will be interesting.
Lin Yue has taken over at the top of the leaderboard.
David Buday has come from eighteenth to third.
The Mexican and the Germans still holding their own.
Tom Daly has worked his way up the field as well.
Matthew Mitchum just ahead of the cut.
Nick McCrory, Riley McCormack are the ones under pressure.
12 remember the cutoff to go through to tonight's final.
The standard has gone up a notch or two from last night.
Well undeniably Roger, you see this across competitions, qualifying the top boys just want to get there and they're holding something back and not now.
David Bodeo has transformed overnight.
He's now in third place.
Reverse three and a half somersault for his fourth dive.
3.3 the tariff.
Well he'll be relieved to have done a good job with that.
That was the dive that got him only 44 points last night.
Eliminate that from his total.
Come up with something better which he's certainly done here and he'll continue to be knocking around the top five.
Matthew Mitchum made mention of this man when he was talking about the inconsistent performances across the preliminaries.
And David Baddai, he doesn't belong in 18th position and he won't be there.
Eighty five point eight.
Things going much better for the American.
Jose Guerra.
He too has improved significantly from the preliminary competition.
He's up into ninth place.
Armstand reverse triple somersault for his fourth dive in his sixth dive program.
Three point four the tariff.
Excuse me.
This was his top scoring dive last night and he might be able to do the same again.
I wonder what the penalty would be for dragging that towel into the pool with you.
experienced either.
He was fifth in Beijing.
Athens didn't go so well.
Twenty-fifth, fourteenth in Sydney.
Oh, he's not looking too comfortable.
Back problems plague many of these top athletes in the pool and at the gymnastics and the sports are closely related as I'm sure you're aware.
Oh, that's better, much better.
He's been a little inconsistent through his first three.
He's the one who missed a couple of years through injury.
He's a proven competitor and I think he's just proved it.
Well he needs to lift himself up the standings in an 89.1 for Galperin.
His best dive so far.
His second dive was a 37.4 so he's really got to rattle up some big numbers with his closing two dives as well as that one.
Here comes the heartthrob.
Young Tom Daley.
I'm feeling he's still going to be young Tom Daley in about 10 years time because everybody just has that view of him in Britain.
Forward four and a half somersault.
Nicely done again.
Gives the crowd plenty to cheer.
Willing him on.
willing the judges to give him a good score as well.
Just short of the vertical bit again he's one of these divers as the top boys can just minimizes the splash what whatever the entry angle.
It's a real knack to that.
Well, GB Success has stunned many of the home fans, I can tell you, and Tom Daley has to turn that expectation into inspiration as many other athletes have done and found that the crowd support has really taken them the extra mile.
88.8 and again, Daley's improving across the board.
Victor Minibyev is tenth.
Arm stand back double somersault two and a half twist three point six and needing to maintain those standards.
Oh, a little untidy at the bottom.
I'm not sure if he was waving to someone with his toes or just looking for that extension.
From fingers to toes, but he's over rotated.
There we go.
I'm not sure what that achieves except to give us something to talk about, Roger.
Maybe it's like maybe it's like a trigger.
Quite a lot of performers and even golfers talk about the trigger when you're just going to decide when to when to do it.
Yeah.
Make yourself move.
A little forward press.
Victor Ortega from
He really doesn't muck around up there.
Executed well.
Feet just slightly apart on entry, but again from side on, it's one of those little faults you can get away with.
considering the judges position as they study the dive.
78.4.
He's picked up a few marks on his preliminary effort.
Like many of the divers, he says that half his training is actually out of the water.
Two or four hours a day spent in the gym.
Anton Zakharov now, reverse three and a half somersault.
He's down in seventh place.
I think he had a better entry position than the splash indicated.
Sometimes it works the other way.
He's pretty much vertical but just couldn't match that angle with the splash.
He's done well though, 84.15.
Zakharov moving along quite nicely.
Scores in the 70s and 80s.
Riley McCormick.
His fourth dive is an arm stand back triple somersault.
We're getting through the dives about one every 20 minutes, which is about 10 minutes less than last night.
So getting a chance to get into a little bit more of a rhythm once he gets into that arm stand position for the back triple somersault.
Very good.
So 3.3 the tariff.
69.3 for this one last night.
Not the tightest tuck position you'll see.
Like the entry angle.
Kicks it out from the platform.
Very tidy.
Judges approve with those eights.
79.2.
That keeps him in the hunt for a place in tonight's final.
from Cuba.
Still has work to do.
Arm stand back, double somersault, one and a half twists.
Three point two with a lower tariffs.
So, execution has to be exemplary if he's going to make a run for the final twelve.
wonderful entry not quite square for my view but the position with the at least as far as vertical is concerned was a one and the splash not there at all so a good impression well one of those nines is going to count because there was three of them and that will help
And an eighty three point two.
He's picked up thirteen points for that dive from the prelims.
That's a bonus.
Now, the four men who retained their ten meter title were Samuel Lee, Robert Webster, both Americans, the famous class Ibiassi from Italy and Greg Louganis, the most iconic figure perhaps in diving.
Matthew Mitchum, pretty iconic himself in his own way.
Reverse three and a half somersault.
Oh, well, he must have slept well.
I think he just fancies it now.
You just get that impression, don't you?
He's happy to be here.
And a happy competitor is often a good one.
Boy, wait for this.
The judges really like what they saw from Mitcham here and with good reason, near perfection.
He is a showman.
It's just the joy of competition.
I like to see that from anyone.
And a 90.75.
I think the other divas will be looking across and just thinking, oh oh, he might be on a little bit of a bit of a ride.
Nick McCrory has rather more pragmatic problems ahead of him.
Twelve right on that cut line.
Reverse three and a half somersault for the American.
Well, that's beautiful.
Dive by dive, we're just seeing the standard improve.
I know we're moving up to the higher seeded divers, but they're not disappointing.
They're living up to their rankings.
Solid nines here, McCrory.
Well, this is what we should be seeing.
We want to see the medals tonight decided on excellence, not on somebody making a mistake or slipping out of it.
You know, you want to see the top divers really pressed into something that dazzles and gets this crowd right up on their feet.
Alexander Bondar.
Fourteenth place and fighting to stay in the competition with a back
Got it.
Got all of it.
That's a great dive from Bondar.
States his ambitions as being wanting to become an Olympic champion and then sports minister, if that's OK. We like ambition.
There's nothing wrong with a sports minister being a former athlete.
Know something about it.
certain Seb Coe has gone into the more political sphere and done all right with these games so who knows in the future.
It's been an outstanding experience for all of us and as an outsider I must say that it's been an absolute pleasure to be here and see a well-run games and totally enjoyable experience.
Well said.
Ivan Garcia having a good morning.
Fourth arm stand back double somersault, two and a half twists for the Syncro Silver Medalist.
Yes, he just sort of leant into the dispatch from the platform then pushed off and the hesitation in the end led to some indifferent execution.
Sevens, but he would have liked more.
I think he's going to be okay.
He's come in as the sixth highest.
He's only had scores in the eighties.
That'll get the job done.
But that one wasn't his best.
And eighty-one, his lowest score so far.
The second of the two Mexican divers, they're both from Guadalajara.
he's got a German Sanchez inward four and a half somersault 4.1 this is a big one this is his toughest dive he nearly got a hundred for it last night
Well, I can't see that getting around 98.
High tariff.
So if you get most of the value out of it, then you're going to get a very good score.
But the feet were apart there and the splash not ideal.
And the judges didn't miss that little form break or the splash, of course.
That's the most obvious indication of a problem with the entry.
Straight into the analysis.
Martin 86, instead of a 98.
A 12-point slip there.
Talking of let slip, Martin Wolfram has just aged back a bit after a really impressive start.
Again, a newcomer to this level of competition.
Back three and a half somersault, 3.6.
Still sitting in fifth place.
Good effort, Wolfram.
He was one of those divers last night who climbed up the rankings very consistently after his second dive.
He went from 19th to 10th to 8th to 6th to 4th.
So he really moved into the competition with some momentum.
might be tempted to have him as a bit of an each way because quite sure just how much he can pile on but he's he's done very well.
Eighty-six four.
Sasha Klein more experienced German diver.
Twenty-six years of age serves in the army.
Back
Well, very nice again.
He's so consistent.
His dives last night ranged from 81 to 92.
Left him the third highest qualifier.
In that respect, he's like our Chinese divers that just doesn't give you anything bad.
So he's going to be, he's going to be thereabouts.
If he can just pull out a moment of inspiration, he might fancy his chances of getting on the podium this evening.
Lin Yue now leading the field, forward four and a half somersault, 3.7 for the 21 year old.
Remember, he's just coming off a dive of 102.
And last night, this one earned him 92.
And he's taking the challenge to Choubo.
The medals aren't on the line yet, but he is making a statement saying, I'm going to be putting the pressure on.
He is a long way up from that wide shot.
Three stories up, if you like.
Perfect form as he enters the water.
Ninety-four, three-five.
Looks disappointed with the ninety-four.
He's very hard on himself.
Lin is five-four and eight, stone five.
Tubo five-three and nine-two.
Quite a compact, powerful figure now.
Back three and a half, somersault.
And a lot of Tubo's power, evident there, comes through those strong thighs
Big knee bend here.
Up and away.
And that allows him to get through those somersaults so quickly.
Look for the water.
And then say to the judges, what have you got for me?
Well, nine and a halves.
And a 10 in there, but the 10 goes out.
That's one of the top two.
He's back.
Oh, 102.6, if you don't mind.
And that's his first triple digit score for the competition.
Two Chinese divers are definitely pushing each other in this competition.
two has been beaten by Lynn this year.
There's the leaderboard after round four.
China one and two.
David Budaya still doing well.
Sasha Klein and Martin Wolfram and Tom Daly just working his way up the field in seventh now.
Here's what really matters this morning.
Victor Minibiah twelfth and Bondar from Ukraine.
Well, he's point seven five behind him.
Little bit more of a gap to
the Russian and the Ukrainian.
Not that there's any rivalry between those two camps anyway, but only 0.6 between first and second.
So a real battle at the top, a real battle on the bubble, and a great little session unfolding here.
And we're lucky to be here, Roger.
It's just the joy.
And those watching who've got tickets for tonight will feel even luckier still because they know for the atmosphere the tension is going to rise yet again.
And David Budaya has come out here this morning and made sure he's in the frame to be a serious contender.
I don't want to say for the bronze medal position but
He is third after four dives.
Back three and a half somersault there.
A little splashy on landing, if I can put it that way, but David is diving much more to his experience and reputation here in the semi-final than in the prelims.
He's just folded that over a little to create the bigger than desirable splash.
He wasn't far from vertical.
and eighty-two point eight.
Bronze in the synchro where the great advantage of the synchro is you've only got one Chinese opponent to beat as it were.
Whereas here with two individual competitors then it makes it doubly difficult to get on that podium.
Tenth wants to get into that final tonight.
Reverse
Well, again, he jumped well out from the platform, but in no way did that stop him getting through the somersaults and he's done an excellent job with the entry.
Minimal splash here, even if he wasn't quite at the vertical.
Yes, he was at a bit of an angle.
Judges liked it.
And the seventy nine to
Just a modest tariff there of 3.3.
Gleb Gauperin started off the preliminary round so well.
Very quickly into his reverse three and a half somersault.
Straight off the board as soon as he was called.
17th after four dives.
This dive only got him 34.65 last night.
It was the one that nearly tipped him out of the top 18.
He's got so much to do to get into the top 12 because he's had one very bad dive of 37.
His second make up some ground here with an 89.1.
So he's potentially making a late run into the 12, but lots to do still.
Well, Greg Galford had barely hit the water before the raw started to build up to announce Tom Daly onto the platform.
Daly getting more into his stride.
Up into seventh, back three and a half somersault for the 2009 world champion.
Back three and a half somersault then.
Piked.
That's a great effort.
You know, I don't know how much mental damage is done by doing a dive badly, but this one, last night, 39.6, but he has nailed it.
No problems at all.
Where was the splash?
Not there.
and you're getting a very strong impression that not only will he be in the final, he's a contender with that ninety-one point eight and that's now Tom's best dive of the competition last night and today.
We'll boost his confidence.
No end.
Victor Mini Bive living on the edge.
Now, twelfth position.
Now, it's a back
Takes his time.
Really takes his time.
Well, like Daly, Minnibah have had a bit of mental baggage to leave up on the platform with that dive that yielded you less than 50 last night.
Great push off the platform.
Beautiful straight legs in the pike.
Reaches for the water.
The feet coming over just a tiny amount.
pressure on as we get laid into this competition to force your way into that twelve.
Ninety-one point eight.
Huge.
Well timed.
Just when he needed the boost of the points.
Victor Ortega back in eighteenth and maybe just wanting to complete his Olympic experience with a couple of solid
Well, better.
I think he's one of those competitors, Roger, doesn't like to leave himself hesitating up there too long for the negative thoughts to enter.
He's straight into his work.
This is one of his better dives here in the semi.
It hasn't been his session.
Solid eights, though.
had more success as a synchro diver.
Sixth in the Beijing Olympic Games.
Anton Zakharov.
Ninth place.
Fifth dive.
Arm stand back.
Triple
Oh, he didn't hold it for too long up there and maybe not for long enough.
That's a poor dive for Zakharov.
A shocking angle coming in to the water, hence the big splash.
Too late, kicking it out.
He was almost at 45 degrees and a 36.75.
Oh, that will hurt.
could have cost him a place in the final.
That one mistake.
That's what it's all about.
It's the the pressure knowing that you cannot afford to blow one dive and succeed.
Riley McCormick close to the top twelve.
Fourteenth.
Reverse three and a half somersault.
Might just see this as a chance to cash in after
Very good.
So when you're eliminating from eighteen down to twelve and you're on the bubble, you're starting to look around saying, who am I going to beat here?
McCormick might have slipped ahead of a couple with this.
It's an excellent dive.
It's the real competition here this morning is down in this sort of ninth to fifteenth because they're the ones who are under the most pressure
79.2 there for McCormick.
Better result than last night which was a 64 for that dive.
This is Yancla Aguila from Cuba looking to reach the final for the first time.
16th place might just be a stretch too far for him.
Reverse three and a half somersault.
Well, Yenklert stormed home last night in the prelims, going from 19th place to 12th to 10th in his last few dives.
This one, not such a good result.
Just coming in at that less than ideal angle.
It's all in the timing of kicking out from the last somersault.
Now, Mr. Mitchum, what have you got for us this time?
Armstand back, triple somersault, 3.3 the tariff.
Armstand seems an awful long way up for one of the most powerfully built divers in world diving, really.
Expect the unexpected from Matthew.
Pretty good.
I think he's safely through.
This was only a 66 dive for him in the prelims.
Not his perfect line on entry that we saw from his previous dive.
He's just edging closer.
Grimace this time.
He knows he left a bit out there.
had a severe abdominal muscle tear which cost him a place in last year's World Championship.
So, he's got ground to make up.
Nick McCrory in eleventh place.
Looks a lonely figure up at the top of that ten meter board.
Just over thirty-nine feet in old money.
Back three and a half
Very good.
79.2 for the dive last night brings a smile to the US coaching staff.
Great height off the platform so he's already through his first somersault before he passes it on the way down.
Give yourself time to get the entry angle just right which he did
started off as a swimmer and said that um switch to diving because he looked more fun having a bit more fun with those scores i mean yes just watching that line in the pool hour after hour lap after lap how much fun is that why don't you jump off 10 meters alexander bonda with a reverse three and a half somersault 13th he's still full of hope here
Well, that's one of the best entries of the night.
The dive got him 89.1 last night.
There's a little sort of vibration of hips and legs here as he straightened out for the entry.
too quick for the judges to worry about that though and an 89.1 and Bondor is going well.
Mike just cashed in there on his countryman Sakharov I think who had the disappointing dive.
Now we're getting back up more towards the top end with Ivan Garcia from Mexico.
Sixth place after four dives.
Now a reverse three and a half somersault tucked.
He qualified sixth.
He's sitting sixth at the moment.
Almost had too much time.
He's so quick with his somersaults.
So he's just overcooked it at the end.
Well, he's got one and a half done by the time he goes past the platform and spotted the water so early that he pushed himself past the vertical.
But as he comes out of the split tuck, ankles together, there's lots to like about that dive.
74.25, the difficulty just 3.3.
Just a reminder that all these divers not only had to qualify from last night, but just to be in London, they did well in last year's world championships or were continental champions or through the Diving World Cup this year, which carries on around the world.
German Sanchez reversed three and a half somersault
With work to do again.
Oh, that's a very good dive.
He's entitled to like this one.
Up and away.
Not too close to the platform to give us any palpitations.
Slight twist of his angle of entry here.
Vertical, but not square.
But the judges didn't seem to mind.
Three nines there and an 89.1.
And again, that's a kind of error, Roger.
We need a couple of angles to pick that up.
Right, back on track after that.
Martin Wolfram from Germany, 20 year old from Dresden, back two and a half somersault, two and a half twist, fifth after four dives.
Well, it looked like it was going to be untidy at entry.
The feet seem to be all over the place, but he's again controlled the splash very well.
Good push off the platform through this complicated dive.
Finds the water.
Good, but he's got better.
Remember the World Championships last year, he didn't even get through qualifying, finished 20th, so he's really trained on here.
86.4.
Sasha Klein completing the encouraging position for Germany.
That was a reverse three and a half somersault for his fifth dive.
Was ranked fourth.
And he received an 89.1 for this dive last night.
But that was scoring nines.
So you won't get that this time.
The three point three tariff.
It's grimacing through those tight rotations.
Seventy four to five, so fifteen points slip there.
at the top of the board.
Having a good competition for number one ranking tonight with Cubot.
This is Lin Yue with an armstand back double somersault two and a half twist.
well that's his biggest splash of the night well the morning aren't we sorry and that dive that got him 91.8 in the prelims won't be doing so again he got off on the wrong angle there one arm was stronger in the push off than the other he never had it online
And he's dominated the synchro scene over the last few years.
The reigning Olympic champion, 10-metre synchro.
World championships in 2007 and 2009.
But Thubaut has hogged the individual limelight.
Now if he gets this, it's a 100-point dive.
It's his toughest tariff, 3.7.
Forward four and a half somersault tucked.
not quite he's short on the entry so he's just showing the rest of the field that he can make mistakes very high tariff dive though so he's going to score well no mistake about that but the hips still bent at entry and it doesn't matter that it's Troubo the judges
have to be totally objective which they have been here they've seen that mistake 94.35 is still a good score but five less than for the same dive last night it's a bit like competing against some of the Kenyans on the track you've got to believe that you can win it and not just
Take it for granted.
They're still top of the pile, Thubaud and Lignouet, David Boudia.
But look, Tom Daley up into fourth.
That's what's getting the crowd cheering here.
Thomas, Martin Wolfram and Sascha Klein from Germany still holding their own.
Matthew Mitchum, the right side of the line.
Jose Guerra and the man really under pressure is Riley McCormack but German Sanchez has seen his program fall away dramatically and really rather surprisingly.
Yes the Mexican competitors qualified fifth and sixth but it could be only one of them will make it through on those positions and we have to keep an eye on Matthew Mitchum's last dive too.
He's riding him into the final too early he's under some pressure
Inside the 12 at the moment, but only just.
Sixth and final series of dives.
These divers have been competing now for about an hour and 37 minutes to get through five dives.
Organizers have got the competition moving along as swiftly as possible.
And now it's the American from Abilene, Texas, the 23 year old and the bronze Synchro Medalist.
third after five rounds back two and a half somersault two and a half twists in there as well and that man is safe stumbled into the semi-final in last position but he's going to be much higher up the rankings where we're expecting to see him and in contention tonight you'd have to say he's diving now according to his reputation and his results
Very strong man.
Great core strength.
Five foot nine.
One of the taller divers on show here.
And a ninety-three point six.
Very consistent session he's had.
That's his highest dive.
Good finish.
You'll like that.
Jose
12th back two and a half somersault two and a half twist diving for a place in the final tonight might just have done it too 3.6 the tariff through the twists into the water at a good angle low splash
that's given the judges something to admire.
Coach looks a little concerned but He's the thirty-three year old.
Remember?
The real standard bearer for diving in Cuba and the oldest diver in the competition.
Gleb Galperin and a twenty-seven year old from Moscow trying to put all those injury problems of the past behind him.
Back
Might well be his farewell show back down in 16th.
Galperin would love to take back his second dive which got less than 40 points and 84.6 and he needs a few things to go right for him to make the 12.
Next up it's the local hero, it's Tom Daly who has been getting better and better and will be desperate to produce a strong dive to finish his program and send him into tonight's final with the confidence that he surely craves for.
Fourth after five dives, reverse three and a half somersault with a comparatively modest 3.3 degree of difficulty.
There we are, he's through.
Hardly a splash at all.
Rips through the three and a half somersaults.
He's the man most of the crowd have come to see and they are giving him a major send-off into tonight's final.
All the judges though, that's the all-important thing.
All the applause echoing around this aquatic centre.
And an 89.1, count him in.
There's another man confirming his position in the platform final.
very smiley young man apart from when the competition is on.
So, he will have a little bit more to relax about after this morning.
Victor Mini Bive, seventh, back two and a half somersault, two and a half twist which you want to make sure that he just gets through tidily.
Oh, that's good.
He's in as well.
A long way to fall from seventh to thirteenth and he could even lift himself a place.
This was very good.
There's the water.
I'm going in straight and he certainly does.
whole different level of competition so far this morning.
We're getting far more of those eight and a halves and nines, a bit more like it.
And the Russian support crew very happy with that.
That's his highest score of the semi ninety three point six.
So he's in.
Victor Ortega from Colombia.
Right down in 17th and just wanting to walk away from the Olympic Games with a good dive behind him.
which he does.
Reverse three and a half somersault, worth 3.3.
I wonder if that's his last dive in Olympic competition.
He's 24.
He's got his sights set on being a lawyer.
Second Olympic Games.
Not a bad effort overall in your sporting career, is it?
Two Olympic Games.
But from Colombia down to Brazil, it's not that far, is it?
He might just be tempted to go one more cycle.
I wonder.
That'll be his decision, of course.
79.2.
Well done.
training so demanding though trying to carry two careers and compete at the very highest level that's tough Anton Zakharov down in 15th place he collapsed in his program a little bit back two and a half somersault two and a half twist well he's a little bit of a chance here with a 3.6 tariff on this one
This is going to be very tight.
Pressure on around the cut.
As the eight and a half's come in for Zakharov.
One judge has thrown in a nine and a half here.
I'm not sure where that comes from.
Or nine, beg your pardon.
He'll have an anxious 15, 20 minutes.
Riley McCormick from Canada.
13th.
Diving to give Canada a representative in the concluding event in the pool tonight.
Back three and a half somersault.
pressure on this dive.
One outside the top twelve.
Oh, spectacularly good.
High tariff with this one.
It was his best dive last night.
He obviously likes this one.
He saves his best till last.
Canada have picked up two bronze in these Olympic Games in the diving and they they'll want to be here competing tonight.
Not just as spectators.
Boy, he might have done it.
A big sprinkling of nines across the scoreboard for him.
And Matthew Mitchum can only applaud the work of his opponent here, 97.2.
Whoa, that's one of the top dives of the night.
Talk about digging deep when it's necessary.
Heinkler Aguila is bringing up the bottom of the table at the moment.
Back two and a half, somersault two and a half twist to end his Olympic campaign.
better finish from him.
Pretty disappointing considering he came in as the tenth qualifier.
Couldn't make the final in Beijing and again, it's a semifinal ranking for him.
Top eighteen in the world.
Now there's a lot of pressure on this dive for Matthew Mitchum who's coming in to his last dive ranked 11th but those around him are really finding extra points with their last dive.
The Olympic champion wants the chance to defend that title tonight and cannot afford anything less than his best now.
It's his highest tariff dive.
Back two and a half somersault, two and a half twist.
Oh, I don't know.
I don't know.
Some concerned faces amongst those interested in his outcome.
This was a big splash.
Looked to be struggling and I think we've just lost him.
These scores aren't enough.
And that will be a loss to tonight's final.
He was still one of the big names being mentioned in the medal frame coming into this competition.
And it will be a real shock and a real story if Matthew Mitchum has missed that cut.
And he is flirting with it on those marks, Steve.
Well, that 70.2 is his lowest scoring dive of the night and had the highest tariff.
So I should say morning again.
a man who produced the the end dive to end all end dives four years ago is suffering the opposite now nick mccrory's got his own worries he's 10th back two and a half somersault two and a half twist needs a steady points return i think that was steady enough
Good push off the platform.
One of the taller divers here, 5'11".
It's a lot of body to get around and up into the air, but he does it very efficiently.
And he should be OK.
In fact, he will be.
Look at the number of competitors left and where he sits.
McCrory's in.
Alexander Bondar, ninth after five dives.
Back two and a half somersault, two and a half twist, looking over his shoulder.
Very nice entry.
Bondor.
Oh, there is the disappointment of Matthew Mitchum.
I think he knows he's gone.
tearful end to his campaign.
The leg form here, Londa not so special and 79.2.
One of his lower rank dives for the session but he's okay, he's qualified.
on our little scoreboard here up in our commentary position as it's confirmed who can't be displaced.
A little Q is coming up next to their name but Mitcham knows it's no final for him.
Even Garcia eighth.
Finishing with a forward two and a half somersault with three twists with a 3.8 tariff.
didn't finish it as he would have liked.
Head came down pretty quickly as he looked to get into the twisting section of his dive and over the legs come.
That should do it though.
And a 79.8.
So he's in.
It's been a strange session, though, for this man.
German Sanchez, who was looking very impressive at one stage, but he's fallen away.
He's back down in 14th, forward four and a half somersault, 3.7.
Needs a big haul from that.
Twenty-year-old from Guadalajara, silver medallist in the synchro with Ivan Garcia, does not want to be split from his countrymen for tonight.
This was his lowest scoring dive in the prelims.
I think he's making amends here.
He only got sixes for it last night, but today some eights and a good tariff of three-seven.
And an eighty-eight point eight.
He's waiting.
Martin Wolfram in fifth place.
Forward four and a half somersault to end.
Three point seven the tariff.
Very nice.
A little short on the entry.
Not much.
And a big tariff.
He's had a good competition so far though.
Responding to the challenge of this, the very highest level of competition which is pretty new to him.
They're all in.
Sasha Klein in sixth place will also looking to be joining the party and should do unless something disastrous happens to his back.
Two and a half somersault, two and a half twists.
He's been consistent.
Well, no disaster there, but not quite what he would like to show us in the final, but he'll be there.
The judge is very much of the same view about this dive, which got him 81 in the prelims.
And again.
Nothing if not consistent.
Now, the battle within the battle.
Lin Yue from China, second behind his countrymen, back two and a half somersault, two and a half twists to conclude an impressive program.
Well, impressive again.
Lin Yue, there was a little bit of a leg form break at the top of the dive.
But he got it all back together very neatly.
Just there the ankles drifted apart but restores his usual immaculate position as he enters the water.
So, will it be China 1-2 going into the final?
These scores don't carry forward of course, Roger.
They may well carry forward in one or two divers' minds as they see the standards that the Chinese divers have set, not that it comes as any surprise at all.
And leading the field has been 19-year-old Chu Bo, the bookie's favourite.
Back two and a half somersault, two and a half twist.
Well, why not end the session with something near perfection?
Troubo could give us another 100-point dive here.
Such power off the platform.
And through the rotations.
Diver of the year for the governing body, Fina, last year.
And another tantalizing display from him.
Going to be great tonight.
Well, very close to the 197.2.
He's the top man.
He is the one to beat.
They are the ones to beat.
The two Chinese divers.
Tom Daly getting a massive cheer as he leaves the pool.
Fourth place.
Matthew Mitchum, though.
He will be devastated.
He has just missed out by one spot, Matthew Mitchell.
No opportunity to defend his Olympic title.
So there's one that the rest of the field does not have to worry about.
And he could have been a threat, but he didn't make it.
David Boudia has come out of this from 18th up to third.
Martin Wolfram just behind Tom Daley there.
Minibaev, McCrory, Sascha Klein.
Germany doing well.
Jose Guerra making the cuts.
Even Garcia, Alexander Bondar, Riley McCormack scrambling aboard.
The big headline to miss out Matthew Mitchum and German Sanchez as well who was so promising before also misses the boat.
Gleb Galperin too will be disappointed as will those six who don't go forward but Matthew Mitchum is the negative headline story if you like from tonight and I'll save you any accusations and bias to say that from an impartial point of view the competition will be a little bit
the less for the for the lack of someone like him.
So he can't really have any complaints, Roger.
He missed that 12th position by some 13 points.
We know he's come here less than in the condition he was four years ago, not able to throw the difficulty into some dives, but he didn't finish well.
He had the opportunity to confirm his place, wasn't able to make the most of that last dive that had the highest tariff, and so
He can have no complaints.
He knew what his limitations were coming here and as much as we like watching him dive, I think if he'd made the 12 in the form that we've seen from him, he wasn't going to threaten for the medals.
His personality, though, is something that adds to the whole sense of occasion here.
Mind you, this competition so far today has really cranked up the anticipation and Tom Daly's progress will certainly crank up the volume.
There'll be 17,000 in here tonight.
It is one of the top tickets in town, if you were lucky enough to get it.
And really, the level of competition has risen here because
It was fierce especially for that last place on board and we've got an idea of what is to come tonight.
It's going to be a great competition.
The crowd will lift the roof off for Tom Daley.
There'll be generous applause and real excitement about what the two top Chinese competitors have for Chou Bo and Lin Ye.
And Budaya coming from last qualifying position to third.
Maybe he's got more to offer as well, but so much to look forward to, Roger.
So can anyone produce the performances to challenge these Chinese divers who have shown their nerve and their skill.
They're impassive on the outside and they just let their diving do the talking.
Matthew Mitchum waves farewell though to this Olympic final.
We're back here tonight at seven o'clock.
It'll be great.
Platform final, the last event here in this diving pool.
Make sure you don't miss it.